A Guide to the William Bartow Rowland Operations Manuals, 1976-2002
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
William Bartow Rowland Operations Manuals, 1976-2002
Library of Virginia
41386
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William B. Rowland of Richmond, Virginia, 9 August 2004.
Biographical Information
William Bartow Rowland, Jr. earned his bachelor's degree from Augusta College and his master's degree from the University of Georgia. He served as deputy director of the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, director of Executive Services in the Office of the Governor, and deputy director of the Department of Planning and Budget. After leaving government employ, Rowland served as a consultant to government through his firm, The Consultancy. He and his wife Janice Flanders Rowland had three children. Rowland died 30 January 2006 in Richmond, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Operation manuals, 1976-2002, compiled by William Bartow Rowland (1943-2002), while serving as Events Coordinator for the Commonwealth of Virginia. The manuals cover operational procedures for a wide range of events from the bicentennial celebration of the battle of Yorktown and the voyage of the replica of the ship Godspeed to Governors' Conferences and agency meetings, as well as a postponed visit by officials from the Soviet Union. Collection also includes reports on various aspects of state government and on the Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation and the celebration of the 400th anniversary of Jamestown settlement.
Contents List
- Operations Manuals, 1981-1984 (Box 1)
  - Capital Outlay Budget Tour, 11-15 May 1981.
  - Capital Budget Presentation, 3 April 1985. Held in Richmond, Virginia. Located in same notebook as 1981 Capital Budget Tour.
  - Where America's Independence Was Won (Yorktown, Virginia), 14-19 October 1981, volume I.
  - Where America's Independence Was Won (Yorktown, Virginia), 14-19 October 1981, Volume II.
  - Salute to Virginia Olympians, 18 September 1984. Held in Richmond.
  - We Have It Made in Virginia, 5 September 1984. Held in Northern Virginia. Located in same notebook as Salute to Virginia Olympians.
  - 50th Annual Meeting of the Southern Governors' Association, 8-11 July 1984. Held in Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Commissioning of the Godspeed, 19 November 1984. Commissioned at Yorktown.
- Operations Manuals, 1985-1988 (Box 2)
  - Godspeed: Governor's London (England) Schedule, 27-30 April 1985.
  - Godspeed: Ports of Call, London to St. Thomas, April to July 1985.
  - Godspeed: Ports of Call, St. Thomas to Virginia, July 1985.
  - Godspeed in London, April 1985.
  - Godspeed in St. Thomas, Virgin Islands, July 1985. Located in same notebook as Godspeed in London.
  - Godspeed Ceremony of Thanksgiving, 25 November 1985. Held in Jamestown, Virginia. Located in same notebook as Godspeed in London.
  - 11th Annual Joint Meeting of Southeastern United States/Japan Association, 12-14 October 1986. Held in Hot Springs, Virginia.
  - USSR Visit to Virginia, 16-17 November 1988, Cancelled. To have been held in Richmond and Charlottesville, Virginia.
  - Southern Growth Policies Board Annual Meeting, 8-10 June 1988. Held in Richmond. Located in same notebook as USSR Visit to Virginia.
- Operations Manuals, 1988-1992 (Box 3)
  - Southeastern United States/Korea Annual Meeting, 13-15 November 1988. Held in Williamsburg.
  - Health Care Summit, 7-9 June 1992. Held in Chantilly, Virginia.
  - New Governors' Conference: New Governors Seminar, 14-18 November 1989. Held in Charlottesville. Located in same notebook as Health Summit, 1992.
  - Virginia Summit on Drugs: Law Enforcement, 16-17 April 1990. Held in Richmond.
  - Governor's Conference on Rural Development, 20-21 September 1990. Held in Roanoke, Virginia.
  - Southern States and Central America Summit, 28 July 1992. Held in Charlottesville. Located in same notebook as Governor's Conference on Rural Development.
  - Virginia's Readiness for Mass Casualties, January-February 1991.
  - Virginia Center Stage, 10-12 September 1991. Event not held.
- Operations Manuals, 1994-1996 (Box 4)
  - Vision for Virginia: 1994 Agency Leadership Workshop, 11-12 July 1994. Held in Richmond.
  - Southern Legislative Conference Annual Meeting, 16-20 July 1994, volume I. Held in Norfolk, Virginia.
  - Southern Legislative Conference Annual Meeting, 16-20 July 1994, volume II. Held in Norfolk.
  - Implementing the Pretrial Services and Local Community Corrections Acts, 2-5 April 1995. Held in Richmond.
  - Virginia Retirement System: Annual Retreat, 14-16 June 1995. Held in Roanoke.
  - National Council of Professors of Educational Administration Annual Meeting, 8-12 August 1995. Held in Williamsburg.
  - Community Service and Volunteerism Conference, 16-18 May 1996. Held in Virginia Beach, Virginia.
- Operations Manuals, 2000-2002 (Box 5)
  - 25th Joint Meeting, Southeast U.S./Japan, 1-3 October 2000. Held in Norfolk.
  - 2001 Virginia Governor's Conference on Travel and Tourism, 29 April-1 May 2001. Held in Richmond.
  - The Pretrial Act and the Comprehensive Community Corrections Act, 29 April-1 May 2001. Held in Richmond.
  - Council of State Governments 2001 Annual Meeting, 20-24 September 2001. Scheduled to be held in Anchorage, Alaska, but postponed due to 9/11.
  - Council of State Governments Annual Meeting, 5-9 December 2002. Held in Richmond.
- Manuals, Handbooks, Workbooks, etc. 1995-2001 (Box 5)
  - Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation Board of Trustees Manual, 1995.
  - Jamestown-Yorktown Celebration 2007 Subcommittees Workbook, 1998.
  - Jamestown-Yorktown Educational Trust Board of Directors Manual, 1998.
  - 2001 Virginia Governor's Conference on Travel and Tourism, 29 April-1 May 2001, Participant's handbook. Held in Richmond.
- Reports 1976-2000 (Box 6)
  - A Compilation of the First Six Interim Reports of the Commission, July 1976.
  - Governor's Conference on Critical Reevaluation, 23-24 September 1983, Conference Proceedings.
  - The Governor's Report on Critical Reevaluation: An Assessment of the Secretarial System and Proposed Realignments of the Executive Branch, 24 January 1984.
  - Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission, the Virginia General Assembly: House Document No. 20: An Assessment of Structural Targets in the Executive Branch of Virginia, January 1984.
  - Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission, the Virginia General Assembly: House Document No. 21: An Assessment of the Secretarial System in the Commonwealth of Virginia, January 1984.
  - Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission, the Virginia General Assembly: House Document No. 22: An Assessment of the Role of Boards and Commissions in the Executive Branch of Virginia, January 1984.
  - Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission, the Virginia General Assembly: House Document No. 44: Organization of the Executive Branch of Virginia: A Summary Report, January 1984.
  - Guide to State Records in the Archives Branch, Virginia State Library, 1985.
  - Virginia Department of Budget and Planning: Staffing and Treatment in Adult Psychiatric and Geriatric Facilities of the Virginia Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation, December 1986.
  - Virginia Department of Budget and Planning: How to Plan and Implement a Special Event, May 1987.
  - Planning an American Celebration: 1607-2007 Jamestown, ca. 2000.